Hey everyone! Welcome back to the channel!
I'm [Your Name], and today I'm going to show you something really cool.
I built a Personal Finance Tracker app in Python,
and it's completely open source on GitHub!
If you've ever wanted to track expenses, visualize spending in charts,
and manage finances all in one desktop app, this video is for you.
I'm a developer passionate about building practical desktop applications
and teaching others how to code.
On this channel, I share Python tutorials, full-stack projects, and open-source code.
If you like learning by building real projects, subscribe!
This is the Personal Finance Tracker.
Built with Python 3.8, Tkinter, SQLite, Matplotlib, and tkcalendar.
The app has four main tabs:
Dashboard, Transactions, Add Transaction, and Analytics.
Dashboard: Shows total income, expenses, and net balance.
Also displays recent transactions.
Transactions: Lists all transactions.
Filter by income or expense, and delete records if needed.
Add Transaction: Enter new transactions with date, type, category, amount, and description.
Analytics: Income vs Expense, Category Breakdown, and Monthly Trend charts.
Everything is stored locally in SQLite.
Your data stays on your computer. No cloud, just privacy.
Step one: Clone the repository from GitHub.
git clone https://github.com/YOUR_USERNAME/finance-tracker.git
If you don't have Git installed, head to git-scm.com and install it.
Navigate into the project folder:
cd finance-tracker
Next step: Create a Python virtual environment.
python -m venv .venv
This creates a folder called .venv.
On Windows, activate it with: .\.venv\Scripts\Activate.ps1
With the virtual environment active, run:
pip install -r requirements.txt
This installs matplotlib, tkcalendar, Pillow, and other dependencies.
To run the app:
python src/main.py
The Personal Finance Tracker window opens!
Clean, professional, with blue and white theme.
Here's the Dashboard with three summary cards:
Total Income, Total Expenses, Net Balance.
Date range buttons: This Month, This Year, Last 30 Days.
These let you filter your summary instantly.
Let's add some transactions. Switch to the Add Transaction tab.
Here's the form. Pick a date, select Expense or Income,
choose a category, enter amount, add description.
Example: Groceries expense for 1,250 rupees.
Click Add Transaction.
Success! Now add an income entry: Salary, 50,000 rupees.
Switch back to Dashboard.
Summary cards now show: Income 50,000, Expenses 1,250, Balance 48,750.
Transactions tab shows all entries.
Filter by Expense, Income, or All.
Delete Selected removes records. Confirmation dialog appears.
Analytics tab: Three chart types.
Income vs Expense shows totals in bars.
Category Breakdown shows spending by category.
Monthly Trend shows income and expense over 12 months as line graph.
Code structure: src/main.py handles GUI, src/database.py handles database operations.
Key features: Add/delete transactions, filter, charts, local SQLite database, professional UI, Indian Rupee currency.
GitHub repository is in the description. Clone, run, customize, contribute!
Like this video, subscribe for more Python tutorials,
and comment what feature you'd add next!
Thanks for watching! I'm [Your Name]. See you in the next one. Peace!